this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
hi everyone this is a Priyanka raghwan
for software engineering radio and today
we're going to be discussing the GitHub
co-pilot and how it can improve
developer productivity
for this Our Guest is Eddie aftandilian
who works as a researcher at GitHub
Eddie received a PhD in computer science
from Tufts University where he worked on
Dynamic analysis tools for Java he then
went on to Google where he again worked
on Java and developer tools and then of
course he's now a researcher at GitHub
working on developer tools for the
GitHub co-pilot which is an AI powered
code generation tool which is integrated
into vs code in addition to working on
the co-pilot vs code plugin he also
works closely with openai and Microsoft
research to improve the underlying codex
model
so you're a perfect guest for the show
and welcome to the show Eddie thank you
I'm very excited to be here okay is
there anything else you would like
listeners to know about yourself before
we jump into the co-pilot so as you
mentioned my background has been in
various types of developer tools so
Dynamic analysis static analysis tools
at Google and so I have a soft spot for
especially for static analysis and
detecting common problems as part of the
developer workflow and helping
developers write write better code in
that way as well that's great because
the first question I wanted to ask you
before we actually go into the co-pilot
you know considering your background so
there we've had the days of VI and then
we've had the days of whim and then of
course it got better with emacs probably
showing my age now and then we've had
Ides like from Eclipse to vs code to
Sublime Text to IntelliJ what do you
think about this integrated development
environment how has it really
contributed to say developer activity
I think Ides have contributed greatly to
developer productivity so when I started
programming in college we all used vim
and I actually still use Vim today for
certain tasks but when I need to do
anything more substantial I use an IDE
these days it's usually vs code when I
was writing Java it was IntelliJ and
then before that it was Eclipse I find
it very helpful to be able to do things
like jump to definition find usages of
symbols these kinds of things and
autocomplete is a big help especially
things like refactorings and the
built-in warnings and static analysis
are a huge help to me I'm a big fan of
Ides I think IntelliJ is particularly
impressive I think they do a really
really good job with their refactorings
and static analysis and honestly what
I'm trying to do more substantial coding
work if I'm not using an IDE it kind of
feels like I'm trying to work with one
hand tied behind my back I depend
heavily on Ides these days
okay that's great the next question I
wanted to ask you from Ides we've had
this area of research called code
generation or code generator so in
software engineering radio for example
we've done shows on model driven
architectures then you know model driven
code we recently had in episode 517
where we talked about code generators by
another host and there they basically
talked about you know uml specifications
or open API specifications on how that
could be converted into code and I was
wondering if this area of research where
this idea of an AI powered body did that
all come from this area of research
which is yeah code generation I can't
say it did I can see the connection but
you know from my perspective the idea
behind copilot came from a combination
of the existing autocomplete in Ides
that you see combined with sort of the
emerging capabilities of machine
learning models in my time at Google so
Google has this giant monolithic code
base and it has a very nice code search
tool that helps you find code and sort
of has IDE like features that lets you
jump to the the definitions of symbols
and see all the usages of the symbols
and one thing I observed at Google was
that almost any time I was writing a
piece of code someone had probably
written the same code somewhere else in
the Google mono repo and so I was
spending most of my time looking through
code search and trying to find examples
of where other people had done the same
thing that I could use as a template for
what I was trying to do and from there
it seemed pretty plausible that a
machine learning model could be trained
on this type of data and learn those
patterns and then the human no longer
has to go search for these things but
the model can bring you the examples and
adapt them to your context in a much
quicker way that doesn't take you out of
your flow so from my perspective that's
where this idea came from but you know
these types of ideas tend to form
simultaneously from a bunch of different
teams so you know other people may have
come at this from different directions
and ended up in the same place since we
have an expert on the show coming from
that idea there's another one that I
keep seeing in the literature whenever
you Google search co-pilot it's called
the GPT or the generative pre-trained
Transformer what is that could you
explain that to our listeners sure so
GPT is the name for the natural language
models that are produced by openai who
are our partners on copilot so
generative means that they generate text
they generate the next token in a
sequence so you give them a bunch of
text and they try to predict what comes
next
pre-trained it means that the model has
already been it comes trained out of the
box on kind of a general task it's this
task of predicting the next token but it
can also be adapted to other tasks so
sometimes you can just give it examples
of what you want it to do that are
slightly different from what it was it
was pre-trained to do and it will do
them and sometimes maybe you find two in
the model for a slightly different task
by showing continuing training on a
slightly different data set that where
the the target task is a bit different
and Transformer refers to the
architecture of these models the
Transformer is kind of the standard
architecture these days for large
language models they were introduced in
a like very influential paper from 2017
from a number of Google researchers and
they've Transformers have become kind of
the dominant way of constructing these
large language models very interesting
we'll probably Deep dive into this in
the next section but before we do a
little bit more Deep dive into the
co-pilot is there something else that
you could give us a little more context
in terms of what is the exact problem
that the co-pilot is trying to solve
what do you say it is developer
productivity or could it be a training
tool for learning a new language I think
it could be any of those things I think
the core goal is to suggest code to the
user that the user finds helpful for
whatever reason maybe they find it
helpful because it accelerates their
coding or it keeps them in the flow so
they don't have to switch off to do a
search or go look on stack Overflow but
the help is right there in their IDE it
might be that it gives you a skeleton of
you know how to accomplish the task that
you're trying to do and you have to
adapt it a bit but having the skeleton
is helpful and it also could be that
it's helpful when you're learning a new
programming language when you don't know
the idioms maybe you're an experienced
programmer but you don't know how a
particular task is accomplished in a
different programming language but you
know how you would do it in your native
programming language I think copilot can
be helpful for all those things yeah I
can especially remember when I started
programming in Python some time back I
had a big problem going from say Java or
c-sharp to python because it's like
where are the types where's my semicolon
so yeah maybe AI powered body would have
helped and the last question I want to
ask you before we move on to the next
part which is how long was the co-pilot
a research project and when did you
decide to actually release it to a
select set of users to now it's current
after where you're actually charging for
it could you tell us a little bit on
that yeah of course so to my
understanding and I wasn't at GitHub yet
at this time copilot started sometime in
2020 as a collaboration between GitHub
and open AI by the time I joined the
team in March 2021 co-pilot was a
prototype and we released it as a
technical preview to the public in June
2021 and then just this past June June
2022 We Made It generally available to
developers so now in the technical
preview phase we had a wait list and
people had to apply to use it and now
everyone can use it there's a free trial
if you want to continue after the free
trial it's ten dollars a month okay
that's great so now that we've done with
a bit of the introduction of the
co-pilot I want to Deep dive into a
little bit on the workings of the
co-pilot in the sense could you explain
to us how the co-pilot Works essentially
also if you could just touch upon few of
the things that our software Engineers
would be interested in for example how
to get such a good performance
considering your crunching code from a
lot of databases like public reposition
yeah at a core level the way that
copilot works there's an underlying
machine learning model it's called codex
it's related to gpt3 so we talked about
GPT models before it's produced by open
AI it's focused on generating code as
opposed to natural language which is
what the GPT to gpt3 models generate the
way that these models work is that you
give the model a prompt
and the model predicts what should come
next it predicts the next chunk of text
and then under the covers it produces a
let's say a word or a token at a time
and then you form that into a longer
sequence based on probabilities and such
you can ask it to generate a sequence of
tokens up to a certain length that's a
property of the model so in copilot we
connect up to the model by collecting
context from the user's IDE that we use
to construct a prompt and then we pass
that to the Codex model and sort of the
simplest way that you might do this is
you know imagine you're editing some
file in your IDE and your cursor is at
some point let's say in the middle of
the file you could construct a prompt by
just taking the content of the file from
the start up to where the cursor is and
then the model will predict what comes
next the way we do it is more
complicated than that but that's kind of
the Baseline that's what sort of the
simplest thing you could do that would
produce reasonable results let's see
when the model produces a suggestion we
display it to the user in the IDE and we
display it in light colored text we call
it ghost text the user can either hit
tab to accept it just like normal
autocomplete or they can keep typing to
sort of implicitly reject it in terms of
how do we get
such good performance one thing about
the architecture here is that the
underlying codex model it's a very large
model it's not feasible to run it
locally on a user's machine so we run
these models in the cloud we run them on
Azure machines with very powerful gpus
some of the performance we get is
because of the level of Hardware that
we're able to use part of the
performance here is just very strong
Performance Tuning engineering from both
open Ai and our partners at Azure they
put a lot of effort into optimizing
these models and making them run fast so
that we'll get reasonable completion
times less than half a second less than
300 milliseconds in their Ides when
they're using copilot I can vote for
that I've been using it a few times and
yeah it's it's been great that we just
to follow up on that one thing that
struck me was when you talk about the
context of the code base you did allude
to the fact that it looks at the file
till the part where the cursor is but
does it also look at git history of that
file or the whole tree structure of that
is it only the file or the whole tree
structure of the project no it doesn't
look at git history it doesn't look at
tree structure it does look at context
from other files that are open in the
editor
so you know imagine you have multiple
windows and you're flipping back and
forth there's a good chance that the
files you're flipping back and forth
between are relevant to whatever task
you're currently trying to accomplish
and so we inline Snippets from other
files that are open in the editor into
the prompt and we actually see quite a
large performance Boost from doing that
okay so that you can yeah be predictive
considering that you might switch to the
other window okay cool right like
imagine you know you're writing code and
you're doing this thing that I described
earlier you're looking for other
examples of how to do whatever task
you're trying to accomplish but you're
looking at it in your local project I
think that's a pretty common thing that
people do so you can imagine that
whatever you're looking at in the other
window is probably pretty relevant to
the thing you're trying to do in the
current file even though that's not the
file you're working on
okay gotcha the other question I wanted
to ask is would the co-pilot work
differently if you were an English
speaker versus if you were not one now
is there an advantage to being an
English speaker so this is a good
question that we're actively
investigating but I don't have an answer
for you yet okay then I guess the other
thing I would ask is I was following the
co-pilot Twitter handle as well as the
author Twitter handle and one of the
things I remember from your tweets some
time back was that you said you'd use
the co-pilot to build the co-pilot so
can you elaborate a bit on that how did
that work out yeah so I mentioned that
when I arrived copilot was a prototype
it was already a vs code extension those
of us who worked on copilot all used
that extension to further work on
co-pilot so in some sense copilot helped
write itself I found it very helpful you
asked a question earlier or you alluded
to copilot being helpful when you're
learning a new language that was what I
did when I joined the co-pilot team I
previously worked on Java I had been a
primarily a Java developer for the last
10 years and copilot is written in
typescript and then we have other code
bases that are primarily python both
were I'd never written any typescript
and I'd only written a small amount of
python and I found copilot very helpful
in helping me ramp up quickly and write
production quality code in these new
languages I think the neatest thing was
that it would teach me aspects of these
languages that I hadn't seen before so
one anecdote here is sometime I'm in
copilot I was writing some code to take
options from I don't know some arguments
to a function or something and then
merge them with a default set of options
in in this options class and copilot
suggested that I wrap the option type in
this partial type that's in typescript
and what partial does is it takes
properties that are required on a type
and makes them all optional and I guess
the pattern of how you do this option
merging in typescript is you have a
fully formed option or fully formed
options object and you take a partial
object and kind of just lay it on top of
that and override the default values and
you produce a fully constructed options
object with all the required properties
there but I had never heard of this
partial type I had never seen an
equivalent in another programming
language so I had to go off and Google
what partial was but it was exactly what
I needed there and also kind of the
idiomatic way to do this in typescript
coconut taught me this tidbit that I
don't know how I would have learned
otherwise
okay that's pretty neat to hear and I
think that's probably one of the
quickest ways to learn the language
because otherwise you'd be talking to
someone in the office or a buddy
whatever so they are this is good to
know all that stuff anyway now moved
with covet times and things like that so
this is good to know but in in this
context I have an anecdotes I've been
using copilot obviously just before
interviewing you I I wanted to try it so
I've been using it for about a month
mine is a little bit different so I've
been programming and I've come back to
Java after really really long time
actually 15 years and I had this piece
of code that I had to write because one
of my buddies was writing the Java code
was actually not at work for he was on
vacation and the great thing was the
co-pilot actually made me complete this
task in about half a day you know it was
great so I was done which would have
actually taken me some time because
yards which has been Rusty however in
the pr process in the peer review
comments I got that it was very sort of
a novice code and I could have used a
better library and I was wondering
whether it was because of the fact that
co-pilot was not looking at my say the
palm.xml and what version of spring that
I was using and things like that so the
question I was going to ask you is is
there a way to feed back to co-pilot
that hey can you just improve your model
can you look at these files I mean you
did talk about going between the windows
maybe I didn't have my palm.xml open
what can one do
so this is good feedback for us one of
the things about the way copilot works
is that we mostly are looking at code
and not configuration so we're not
actually looking at your pawn.xml even
if you have it open and so another thing
about the way copilot works that we'd
like to improve is that imagine the
underlying model here is trained on
checked in code in public repos on
GitHub so it's well formed and if you're
training to predict the next token
you've always got the Imports at the top
and the Imports are correct otherwise
that code wouldn't have been checked in
but when you're coding your Imports
they're not complete yet so copilot will
assume that the Imports that you have in
the file are the ones you actually want
to use and then try to do its best to
use those but it seems likely that at
least my experience is often I actually
wanted to recommend a library for me
especially when I'm coding in an
unfamiliar language and I don't know
what the common libraries are are I
would actually really like copilot to
suggest the standard library that people
use to do this task so that's an area of
improvement for us okay great so you can
actually start off with something and
then you know build upon that so that
might be a helpful start yeah I agree on
that one other question I wanted to ask
you was also in terms of developer
productivity right let's get into a bit
of that I think there's this paper
called the productivity assessment of
neural code completion I think you're
one of the authors on that the two
points in that paper that really struck
out to me was one was of course the fact
that co-pilots seem to perform better on
untyped languages like JavaScript or
python the second one was that
developers seem to be more accepting of
copilot suggestions on weekends and late
evenings so can you just like you know
break us down from the very interesting
so can you comment on that yeah yeah we
found that that interesting as well so
in terms of performance on different Pro
programming languages we have seen that
that copilot seems to perform better on
JavaScript and python than other
languages we're actually not entirely
sure why like we have a number of
hypotheses but we haven't validated
these but you can imagine maybe for some
reason it performs better on untyped
languages or dynamically typed languages
as opposed to statically typed maybe
it's because they're very popular
languages and so there's more code in
the training set to learn from for those
languages or it could be some other
reason that we haven't thought of one
sort of surprising thing about
performance by language we measure
acceptance rate acceptance rate is one
of our key metrics that's what fraction
of the suggestions that copilot shows
does the user accept we look at a
breakdown by language and sometimes we
see that even less popular languages
sometimes have a higher acceptance rate
than the mean or the median and not sure
why but someone asked this a while back
of they had assumed that copilot
wouldn't perform well on Haskell because
there's probably not a lot of Haskell
code in the training set I went and
looked and actually co-pilot performed
better than average on Haskell and we
don't really know why
but sometimes the behavior of these
large models is surprising you mentioned
the higher acceptance rate on weekends
and evenings so this is an effect that
we've seen consistently like this is a
pretty important effect that we have to
be very aware of when we look at data
when we run AV experiments for example
when we run a b experiments we have to
ensure that we have a full week of data
before we make a decision on the outcome
of the experiment because otherwise
you'll get skewed results based on
over-representation of weekend or
weekdays and in fact it's fairly subtle
like you need to actually look at data
in multiples of weeks and then maybe
there are seasonal effects that we
haven't uncovered yet so this is all
it's very interesting from the
perspective of like how do we make
evidence-based decisions for
improvements and so on we're not totally
sure why this effect happens again we
have ideas but again haven't validated
them my personal hypothesis here is that
on nights and weekends people are
working on personal projects and these
are probably smaller and simpler and
they're just fundamentally easier for
for copilot to deal with they're
probably easier for the developer to
deal with but we don't know why this is
happening it does happen and it
consistently happens we have to take
into account when we do experiments
interesting so I wonder when the data
cannot tell you why something is
happening then what do you do do you do
some behavioral is that I mean just just
out of software engineering context just
wondering yeah well often the data could
tell us we just haven't dug into the
data yet to find out sometimes maybe the
data there you know it's not sufficient
to answer the question and we'd have to
go back and add additional collect
additional data and then we also have to
balance that with whether it's
considerate of users privacy and so on
so sometimes it's just not the trade-off
here is like is it worth answering this
question versus collecting more
information from the user okay
yeah that makes sense that makes a lot
of sense the next question I wanted to
ask you was also in terms of the field
of pair programming do you think that's
going to go away because you have now
this AI powered friend that's going to
help you I don't think so I think people
will continue to repair programming it's
I mean we aspire to be an AI pair
programmer but a human is still a better
pair programmer and so I think you know
people who like to program will continue
to pair program yeah because I I think
in the similar context there's another
question so a few days back we had this
discussion in my company on improving
code quality so I had suggested that you
know we do some apart from having the
human in the loop because oftentimes
you're so pressed for time that when
you're doing the pr review also you
might just approve something without
really going into it because if like if
you're a senior member on the team and
people are like you have like so many
PRS to look at you might just look at
something very quick I suggested that
maybe it's time to have a AI powered
peer reviewer doing first round and then
of course the human comes into the room
uh and that was of course vehemently
struck down in fact I think one person I
had quoted and I was quite taken aback
with the comment he said that is the
downfall of the software development
process but I'd like to know your
thoughts on that what about the pr
review process do you think that is
something that an automated AI powered
body could help I do think so I hope
it's not the downfall of like
I think we're not there yet right so I
think in code review I think it's
feasible in the future that like you can
have an AI bot that helps you review
code I mean in some way you know
existing static analysis tools and
linters are one form of this they're not
machine learning driven typically right
they rely on sort of hard-coded rules
that were produced by an expert but they
are one way to provide automated
feedback on PRS that's one of the things
I worked on at Google and I always saw
our tools as I wanted them to be helpful
to the users I didn't want people to
feel like they were annoyed by these
things or that they had to check a box
to to merge their PR I wanted them to
actually be happy that the tool pointed
out some problem that otherwise would
have been a real bug in their code and
so I think there's a pretty high bar to
making code review comments and sort of
Auto reviewing PR's but it also seems
like something that's pretty plausible
in the not too distant future you could
probably train a model to predict code
review comments you could probably train
a model to predict how to respond to
code review comments and so I think this
kind of thing is is coming I hope it
works well right going back to the
linters and sonar Cube question it would
be useful actually to see if you have
for example it looks at a rule set right
like if you look at the linters they
have a kind of static rule set but it
would actually work good if the co-pilot
suggests fixes based on these this rule
sets within that hard-coded rule set so
it doesn't go to say the public Repose
but looks at your own code to suggest
fixes is that something that's also in
the pipeline and would that mean that
maybe in the future we would probably
have probably not have linters but this
thing that could look at your code and
suggest fixes existing code yeah so this
is I think what you're proposing is like
imagine you're getting uh I don't know
comments on your PR could you imagine an
assistant that suggests the fixes for
you and maybe you just click accept or
it just goes round and round on the code
review you know in the background while
they please sleep I think this is again
I think this is something that's
feasible there's literature in this area
that I think is pretty convincing
Facebook has a tool called get a fix
that they use and they take static
analysis warnings that they see in their
code base and they bind their code
reviews for how do people generally
address the static analysis warning they
might know a rule out of it and then
they ship that as a auto fix like a
suggestion that now comes along with
this type of static analysis warning in
the future and the user can accept it
without having to write the code on
their own another bit of related work at
Google I worked on a system to
automatically repair code that didn't
compile
so imagine you're working on your code
base you know this is in a compiled
language so you run the compiler the
compile fails and then you you go add
the semicolon or fix the type error or
whatever it is and then you rerun the
build and it succeeds so there we've
built a tool that uses machine learning
to figure out how to repair code that
didn't compile based on the particular
compiler diagnostic you got so I think
these are things that are feasible I'd
be interested in working on this type of
thing again in the future
did you say get a fix is the one from
Facebook I shall probably look it up and
add it to the show notes that's right
get a fix okay it's an internal tool at
Facebook okay so we could probably
switch gears and go a little bit into
some of the I would call the maybe like
negative feedback or criticism that's
out there about the GitHub co-pilot so
the first thing I want to talk about is
there's this paper called so I am a
cyber security architect so I was
obviously interested when I was looking
at the ACM journals I was looking at one
of these things which said an empirical
cyber security evaluation of GitHub
co-pilots code contributions I think
that was what it was where it basically
looked at about 89 scenarios for the
co-pilot to produce a code and it
produced about I think quoting from the
paper
1692 programs and they said about 40
percent of the code that co-pilot
suggested was insecure the reasons there
is there is that because co-pilot was
trade not public repos and there was
obviously you know insecure code so I
was wanted your comments on this as a
new attack Vector maybe there'll be
people like creating malicious code in
public git repos and say okay go Pilot's
gonna get that and then people are going
to start having insecure code what are
your thoughts on that and how do you
combat that yeah sure so this is this is
something that's very important to us in
the paper so the the authors created
scenarios in which copilot would have to
write sort of security sensitive code so
they acknowledge this in one of the
threats to validity so it's important to
note that these are not like 40 of all
suggestions that copilot delivers are
insecure it's in these particular sort
of security sensitive scenarios that
this happens and they acknowledge also
that like the reason that copilot
suggests these things is that humans who
wrote the code that copilot was trained
on also make these mistakes I'm sure as
someone who works in cyber security
you've seen that even excellent
Developers
make mistakes
right so in terms of the sort of
immediate things that we recommend we
recommend always running with a static
analysis tool embedded in your workflow
like I said this is what I did at Google
and if your goal is to eliminate a class
of security bug from your code base it
doesn't matter if it was written by a
co-pilot or if it was written by a human
you need to have a checker somewhere
caching these things and blocking people
from merging code with these problems
in terms of from the copilot perspective
what we can do here we Aspire for
copilot to be better than a human
programmer and so we're investigating
this at this point you can come at this
from two perspectives one is you can
analyze the output the copilot produces
and either redact like just don't show
insecure completions or you can
highlight those in the IDE like you
could have an integrated security
scanner or we could package with a
pre-existing Integrated Security scanner
that runs in the ID key the other way
you can come at this is by you know
trying to improve the underlying model
and push it toward generating more
secure code so maybe you filter the
training set for insecure examples one
of the sort of weird properties of these
large language models of code is that
they interpret comments and sometimes
silly comments can improve the code
quality so we've found that things like
just inserting a comment where you say
sanitize the inputs before constructing
the SQL query makes the model actually
the SQL query and then mitigates a
potential like SQL injection attack
so there may also be things on the
prompt construction side we can do to
push the model toward generating more
secure code in the first place I also
just wanted to mention I mentioned my
background in static analysis the
researchers used a tool called codeql a
static analyzer to detect the security
vulnerabilities a fun fact is that a lot
of the team members who work on copilot
previously worked on codeql so security
and static analysis is sort of a
important topic for a lot of the team
members as well okay okay that's good to
know while you're talking about this
running your code through a SAS or code
ql kind of Checker I also remember this
other video that I saw on YouTube from
one of your colleagues at GitHub go find
it where he talked about how do you
check whether the copilot is producing
good code and he actually in the video
there is a thing where it also runs a
bunch of tests on the code is that
something that will be there in the
future so as soon soon as the co-pilot
generates some code it will also produce
the tests in a desktop so that you can
sort of run that is that is that
something that's also going to be coming
together there are a few things bundled
here I'm gonna try to unbundle though
this video is by my my teammate Albert
Ziegler and he is talking about how do
we evaluate the quality of let's say you
know a potential new model that openai
has or you know a potential Improvement
that we have to prompt construction or
these kinds of things right and so what
we do we call this the harness so we do
our first step is to do an offline
evaluation I talked a little bit about a
b experiments we do those but that's
later in the pipeline so the first
filter here is an offline experiment
using the harness and the way the
harness works is we take public GitHub
repos and we attempt to install their
dependencies and run their tests and
then if the tests pass and they have
good coverage of the functions in the
repo then we take a particular function
that has good coverage we delete its
function body and we ask copilot to
generate a replacement then we rerun the
tests and if the test passes we call it
a pass and if it doesn't we call it a
fail and so this is a kind of our first
step in evaluating quality it accounts
for the fact that we don't need an exact
match of what was there we actually
don't want an exact match of what was
there because that sort of implies that
the model has memorized something so we
want to actually a slightly different
completion that has the the same
behavior on the test you asked sort of
as a question whether copilot might
generate tests for you in some future
version it's a bit different from what
we're doing here this is this harness is
about you know evaluating quality for
our team it's not something intended to
be user visible I think generating tests
is another place where co-pilot could be
helpful it'll gamely try to help you
it'll try to write tests too it's just
another form of code it works
in my experience I think it works okay
if if there are example tests where like
if you're in a file with example tests
it'll do a good job of duplicating
what's there and adapting them to
different test cases you're still going
to have to edit them I also think that
test cases are an interesting place
where we could probably do something
special and to make it much better at
writing tests than it currently is okay
the other thing I wanted to ask you in
terms of the negative criticism let's
just get back onto that I was also about
this being a disruptor to the field of
software development so this is
something that I've heard from many
quarters I mean right from literature
online to maybe also informal chats with
a fellow friends Engineers Etc do you
think that maybe it could be the end of
entry level software engineering jobs I
know it sounds pretty harsh but just
curious I don't think so my hope is that
tools like copilot will lower the
barrier to entry and enable more people
to become software Engineers you said
like could this eliminate entry low I I
think it's the opposite I think it will
enable more people to be entry-level
software engineers and to help those
entry-level software Engineers become
more productive more quickly and to
write better code you know if you look
at the past and developer tools we've
seen that new developer tools they help
they augment they don't substitute for
developers you might have imagined back
in the days where everyone was writing
machine code or assembly that like
compilers would cause a fewer compiler
Engineers or fewer developers it's been
the opposite it's opened the field to
more people and empowered more people to
write code and I think copilot will do
the same thing
yeah I think that's probably I think
what he said about the I like the armlet
taught about the assembly to compile the
code yeah yeah that makes a lot of sense
yeah I think it's the way you use the
tools and maybe that we are probably a
lot of the donkey work that we do would
also be gone
yeah hopefully hopefully we can automate
the boilerplate and let developers focus
on the more interesting parts right yeah
yeah can you comment a little bit about
the Privacy angle on the public repos
because I think there's also a lot about
does everything that is public become
open source and then there's also this
term called code laundering which I
think even stack Overflow I think
there's a paper which says uh and I
think IEEE which says a stack Overflow
could also contribute to code laundering
but I think that's again one of the
things that talk about co-pilot because
of the you know searching on public
repos does all of that become open
source can you comment a little bit on
that
sure so I guess first I want to be clear
that we do not use private code to train
the underlying model and we don't
suggest your private code to other users
of GitHub copilot we train on public
repos on GitHub in addition we also
we've built a filter that filters out it
detects and filters out rare instances
where copilot suggests code that matches
public code on GitHub and users have the
choice to turn that on and off during
setup in terms of this idea of code
laundering we think that copiloting
codecs it's similar to what developers
have always done you use source code to
learn and to understand and we think
it's critical that developers have
access to tools like copilot to empower
them to create code more productively
and efficiently
okay it's interesting I'm on the setup
can you just explain that again so when
you actually create a public repo you
have an ability to say whether you want
to contribute to co-pilot or not is that
what you're saying if whether you repo
count or no the filter is for users of
copilot so like I said we we built a
system to detect when copilot is
producing a suggestion that matches
public code somewhere on GitHub and if
you enable that option then copilot will
just not suggest things that are copies
of code Elsewhere on GitHub but maybe
that also makes sense I don't know this
is just like one of the requirement
sessions but uh maybe it also makes
sense that when you set up a GitHub repo
you could also say hey I don't want to
suggest my repo shouldn't be suggested
by copilot shouldn't be used in the
experiment is that something that's
possible I'm curious I can't comment on
that okay but yeah that's maybe
something that we could ask on the
GitHub issues okay that's great Eddie I
think let's go on to the last part of
the show where I want to ask you a few
questions on the future of copilot the
first thing I wanted to ask is the
co-pilot of course requires us to be
online to actually get it to work so is
there something being done to work in
the offline mode
so I think that's an interesting
direction as I mentioned before the the
models that power copilot are very large
and very resource intensive and so it's
not feasible to run them
on you know really any machine
that a person would have any personal
machine we don't have plans in this area
okay unless you have a very what do you
say GPU many gpus on your laptop and
then yeah
you would need
um like you know industrial grade GPS
even your gaming gpus are not okay good
enough can I ask you a question here
sure sure how often do you code without
access to the internet that's uh you got
me there probably never yeah it's been a
while it would be hard right yeah you're
always looking stuff up looking up
documentation going to stack Overflow
and so on that is true but it was
something that struck me was of course I
think I've been lost without the
internet bad confession to make on
software engineering some things of
course uh you know a very comfortable
like for me like right now python know C
sharp I'm fairly comfortable I could do
stuff but yeah something new I mean or
even there this iron is literally
searching stuff online so yeah yeah it's
true since we're doing a national
language processing I wanted to know is
there scope for a voice activated coding
for the future like my job is saying hey
Jarvis please write me some will get me
a binary search tree on my ID is also a
direction yeah I think that's an
interesting Direction and I think the
critical bit there is like what does the
interaction look like how well if you
start thinking about this imagine you
want to like dictate
code that would be really hard you would
be talking about punctuation and there's
a semicolon it would be very awkward and
so being able to do this at a higher
level I think would be really helpful to
people it would be interesting to
explore that okay is that something that
researchers are looking at or no I'm
sure some researchers somewhere is
looking at that okay okay
the other question I wanted to ask you
this is interesting there's certain
languages for example say coborn and you
know the Mainframe Technologies which
actually some companies still have
things running on them but there's
really a dearth of developers in that
field so the companies really struggle
to find people who know those languages
so is there uh something like these
codex models could be claimed on those
languages and maybe a company's pay for
that to run on their Mainframe machines
is that also something that GitHub is
looking at we're exploring offering a
version of copilot that's been adapted
to an Enterprises private code base or a
set of private code bases I hadn't
really considered this from sort of the
Cobalt or like Legacy programming
language angle but it seems possible
that you know such an adapted version
would would work well for for those
kinds of uh Legacy languages that it has
it actually previously seen much public
code for our goal in all of this is to
assist developers and make them more
productive and so I think it's kind of
similar to your earlier question about
learning helping programmers learn new
languages you can imagine this being
helpful for a non-cobo programmer to be
able to productively make changes to an
existing Cobalt code base okay so an
Enterprise Edition would then kind of
help yeah yeah I think so okay I think
that's all I have Eddie and finally
before I let you go I have to ask you
where can people reach you in case they
want to contact you more about yeah sure
so I have a Twitter account it's e of 10
billion so e and then my last name all
one word my GitHub handle is ef10 e a f
t a n I'll definitely write that on the
show notes so thank you for coming on
the show it's been quite enlightening
for me so I hope the listeners enjoy it
thank you very much this was fun thank
you this is Priyanka raghun for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
thank you